foreign
so these are a few questions that I've
gathered up
I have been celibate for some time and
now have the fear that I will lose it
my mind is full of fear and has no peace
yet peace is what I expected to get from
celibacy what am I doing wrong
well you you get you get peace
from losing desire to its sensuality you
losing desire to its sensuality you
don't get peace for celibacy if you
still value sensuality
so celibacy is a necessary prerequisite
to lose the desire towards sensuality
but if you don't if you don't work on
that part mental part of your attraction
to Central objects no celibacy will free
you and give you well it will give you
certainly a less disturbing life a less
engaging life less entanglement in life
being not engaging physically with
sensualities factually less entangling
but yes if you still value sensuality
value essential objects saying no to
them will hurt
so did you did that person expect
celibacy to do the work for him huh
so if I'm celibate if I just abstain
from this sensuality will magically
evaporate from my mind
or did they also on top of that sense
restraint virtue celibacy then make the effort to
virtue celibacy then make the effort to
see the Peril in sense objects to see
the Peril in desire
if not then the peace they were hoping
to get on account of celibacy alone
it's kind of on the level of central
satisfaction again they were hoping that
they will have this pleasure of a
peaceful experience because they're not
engaging sexually anymore
but that's not how it works that would
be too easy then it would say just be
celebrated that's it you're you're in
our hand but no you have to be if you
want to be another hand but in and of
itself it will not result in the
unshakable peace but factually
as I said it will still result in less
entanglements so focus on that Ponder on the benefits
so focus on that Ponder on the benefits
of doing it don't just hope
that it will do the work for you while
you mentally still value the central
objects so once you celibate are you now
spending your time contemplating the
danger of sensitized the lack of
satisfaction the context of you know
entanglement in this entanglement the
value of this entanglement
are you making the effort on that mental
level now that you created a basis
through celibacy and virtue or are you
just celibate and then just sort of
threading water just waiting for the
work to to magically be presented as
completed
it's similar to someone who is
like just doing taking on the rules
taking on certain presets exactly and
then hoping that yeah okay so I
understand now my duties to be certified
okay I'm celibate okay so so where's the
piece
it won't come as a result of it because
you haven't taken it rightly you take
celibacy so that you can tame your mind
you don't take celibacy because that
will do the work for you
so remind yourself for the reasons of
wanting to practice keep that context
work on it
it's again it's the similar flight In
The Sticks you have five sticks light in
the fire with the sticks while you're in
the water
so you can then you realize I have to
come out of this River in order to to
sort of rub the sticks to get the fire
but if you just come out of the river
and you make no effort to rub the sticks
to to light the fire well you won't get
the fire you still won't get the
original result that made you come out
of the water but you have but you have
to come out of the water
so that's a celibacy is not optional for
somebody who wants to practice really
for the results but then once you
celebrate that's not the end of the
practice
coming out of the water yeah now
learning to light a fire and making the
effort to dry the sticks not soak them
not keep them in touch with water even
if you're out in other words stop
valuing sensuality stop hoping for
some degree of central Pleasures after I
become peaceful and so on you have to
say no to that entire domain and you
would say no not by kind of artists
decide to say no but by contemplating
the factual danger of it the factual
lack of satisfaction the factual
perpetuation of the problem and on peace
and that in and of itself would be
enough actually to you to to already
start seeing the benefits of of being
celibate for example and the dangers of
not and the danger is not even if you
don't get some higher results you still
look as well yeah it's still factually
and more freedom comes that way
so a question that's related to this
now that I'm old
celibacy is quite easy
all of my previous passions have faded
and now I dwell equanimous to most
things most but I fear that sickness and death
most but I fear that sickness and death
will still be suffering for me what
should I do next
I think what should I do first is more
likely well you should ask
because celibacy and freedom from
sensuality does not come with old age by
default as I said before it goes underground
as I said before it goes underground
with old age by default means you think
now it's not there because it's too far
gone to see it
and you the reminders of it still being
there are like hard to spot because you
know the Vitality the strength of the
senses the the Zeal it's gone it's just
tired jaded
but the attitude the Assumption of what
where the last days where the attraction
is where these eyes are being satisfied
that's still there and that's now much
harder to see in our Brute
because if
it's sick if a person is truly Economist
then losing the prospect of losing the
body even more exactly if you truly
practice celibacy to its fulfillment I.E
abandoning of central desires
a prospect of sickness and death would
not be frightening at all
and you would not even be doubtful about
it
because that which is going to be wiped
away with sickness and death
is that which you seemingly have no
desire to words anymore
so now your sense is that you're still
very much bound with are even more
invisible remember we spoke in previous
talk senses since organs are always like
negative they're the negative space in
regard to what you look see smell taste
touch so it is defined in return by side
so it is defined in return by side
sounds maltest touches
that is how you can infer and discern
that the organs are there
now when sense uh sites side smells
taste touches have been
bombarding you for decades and decades
and decades and fatigue and you have no
more inspiration or strength and and
like Joy towards the pleasures you just
tie it you just rather not be bolted
means uh your negative spaces of your
senses will be even more invisible now
because they're Factory not being as
defined as before which is what people
confuse this piece
oh look I'm not I'm not Disturbed as
much as I did before yeah because you
you're getting old
but if you truly want to see if you're
peaceful or not well contemplate losing
the dear ones the loved ones
experiencing Misfortune uh can you can
you still experience things on account
of of any account of anything that could
happen to this body
sickness aging
battles of that kind
would you you could remain up perturbed
if you live or die next moment if not
means oh okay so you missed the
opportunity to uproot the dependence on
the negative sense organs negative
spaces of the sense organs
um so now it's going to be even harder
so I guess what you could do is again
spend every minute of your life
contemplating the value of a virtue
sends restraint practice generosity
don't give rise to thoughts of ill will
lots of harm
don't give rise to the sense of false
complacency and safety
on account of things not disturbing you
much and then if you were truly free you have
and then if you were truly free you have
nothing to lose with all these practices
if you were not rooted free well you'll
realize soon enough with all these
practices because you're also eating the
person could take on certain
yeah yeah yeah
the reasons for the ease yeah practice
increased moderation in eating to put it
away because that's still something that
that is something pleasure from yeah I
can't have this sexual part anymore sure
but but sounds touches food
smells of food and comfort physical
comfort being sheltered from the elements and I
being sheltered from the elements and I
don't mean like you know go and live
outside Blizzard or something but
how soft is your bed how soft your
pillows how warm are your blankets
all of that the purpose is one and only
just to break comfort for the body for
the sense organs that you still are
so would you be disturbed on account of
losing those things on the counter maybe
saying no to a degree and and sleep on a
harder bed see without a pillow
how miserable you'll be next day if you
even didn't have proper night of
comfortable sleep
so you can still practice within that
even if you waited because you know
there was that old lady I hold like past
80 or whatever in the suitors
that was
um
had what I think two sons husband lots
of wealth husband passed away
she thought hey why don't I give my
wealth to my two sons and their families
and they look after me so she gave all
of her wealth house everything to the
two sons
and then from you know she would spend
time with one then go and spend time
with the other and on one occasion when
she was like that
arriving at the one son's house before
she overheard him saying oh there she is
coming again like well she has the other
son doesn't she you know the way of
complaining or something so she was
heartbroken the fact that they actually
started despising her
when she actually gave it all away so he
left she left saw the nuns getting
sheltered in the food I thought well
hamadas will become an aunt so I can at
least have someone to sleep and eat so
she didn't even want to practice she was
old she couldn't go Pinder Bud because she
she couldn't go Pinder Bud because she
was old she was just
um would clean up the place when the
younger nuns go for pindapad prepared
everything when they bring the food she
was just like a servant there and once
she overheard one nun talk to the other
about the some aspect of the Dharma that
they heard from the Buddha and then at
night when she finished all of her
chores she couldn't even do the walking
meditation straight because she was so
old she was walking up and down the
corridor propped with against the wall
and contemplating what she heard
and she became an Harahan
so it is still possible
but you do really have to commit to it
like it is your last chance because it
might well be for a long long time